<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true representation of Presbyterian government, wherein a short and clear account is given of the principles of them that owne it. The common objections against it answered, and some other things opened that concern it in the present circumstances. / By a friend to that interest.</title>
            <author>Rule, Gilbert, 1629?-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05065</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2229A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R182954</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53981561</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53981561</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180314</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05065)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180314)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2826:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true representation of Presbyterian government, wherein a short and clear account is given of the principles of them that owne it. The common objections against it answered, and some other things opened that concern it in the present circumstances. / By a friend to that interest.</title>
                  <author>Rule, Gilbert, 1629?-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 3-16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Re-printed by the heir of Andrew Anderson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno Dom. 1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Gilbert Rule. Cf. Wing, McAlpin Coll., NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Presbyterian Church --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Apologetic works --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180314:1"/>
            <p>A TRUE REPRESENTATION OF PRESBYTERIAN GOVERNMENT, Wherein a ſhort and clear Account is given of the PRINCIPLES Of Them that owne IT.</p>
            <p>THE COMMON OBJECTIONS AGAINST IT ANSWERED, And ſome other Things opened that concern IT in the <hi>PRESENT CIRC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MSTANCES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Friend to that Intereſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Licenſed,</hi> April <hi>the</hi> 18. 1690.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Re-printed by the Heir of <hi>Andrew An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon,</hi> Anno Dom. 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:180314:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:180314:2"/>
            <head>A True Repreſentation of Presbyterian Government.</head>
            <p>THat any of the Truths or Ordinances of God ſhould need an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy to be made for them, ſhould be for a Lamentation: For it proceedeth either from the Ignorance or Perverſeneſs of Men. The Principles, and way of <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> have undergone the common Fate of other of the parts of that Religion that Chriſt hath taught: It is the Sect every where ſpoken againſt; and there hath been no ſmall ſtir about that way: And this hath proceeded, partly from the enmity againſt that curb of mens Luſts, and enormities that is in ungodly men: And partly, from want of knowledge of that way, which even they may be under, whoſe Studies and Thoughts are imployed about things of another nature, and not about theſe matters, though they be otherwiſe knowing and thinking Men: Or from prejudice that their Intereſt may fill them with, to the hiding of Truth in this, from their eyes; wherefore we think it our Duty to endeavour the vindication of this our Profeſſion, (with as much brevity and clearneſs as we can attain) by <hi>First</hi> giving a plain account of what we hold. <hi>2dly,</hi> Taking off the moſt material Objections, and theſe that are moſt common, or reproaches that are uſed againſt us; for we have to do not only with men otherwiſe Sober and Judicious, who differ from us: But with many whoſe Temper, Practices, and Deſigns, are not ſuch as becometh the Goſpel. We deſire as to approve our ſelves to our bleſſed Lord and Maſter Jeſus Chriſt; ſo to ſatisfie the Minds of all Inquirers after Truth, but eſpecially to ſtand right in the Opinion of His Majeſty, our gracious Soveraign, of his Grace the King's High Commiſſioner, and of the Noble and Honourable Eſtates of Parliament, who we hope, as Nurſing Fathers to the Church, will owne us in thoſe ways that the Lord owneth us in.</p>
            <p>Our Principles we lay down in a few Propoſitions. <hi>Firſt,</hi> We owne Chriſt the Mediator, as the only Head over, and Lawgiver to his Church; and we diſown and viſible governing Head over the Church, however pretending to act in Subordination to him: becauſe we know none that he hath given ſuch Commiſſion to.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Chriſt as Head of the Church, hath given forth Laws, whereby the Affairs of his Houſe ſhould be mannaged: and hath not left any <hi>Nomothetick</hi> Power in the Church to make Laws for her ſelf (her work being to declare and execute that Laws of Chriſt) and the Laws of the Magiſtrat are not to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point new Ordinances, or Officers in the Church; though he ought to give his civil Sanction to what Chriſt hath appointed, and may make Laws about theſe things that are external to the Church, that is, which are common to her with other Societies.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly.</hi> Chriſt hath appointed Officers in his Houſe, and Declared how they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:180314:3"/>ſhould be qualified, and what ſhould be their work: as in the beginning of the Goſpel, he was pleaſed to appoint ſeveral extraordinary and temporary Officers, that were immediatly called, and extraordinarily Gifted by himſelf, as <hi>Apoſtles, Prophets</hi> and <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> &amp;c. The Apoſtles by Divine derection, did immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chooſe ſome by themſelves for itinerant work (either from amongſt the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, or extraordinary Officers of the Church to exerciſe <hi>hic &amp; nunc,</hi> their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Power; (which Officers we commonly call <hi>Evangeliſts</hi>) ſo we do not find that he appointed any ordinary and perpetual Officers, except Elders, (called alſo Biſhops) and Deacons, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. Of theſe Elders ſome were to Rule the Church, &amp; alſo to Teach her, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7, 17. Others only to Rule, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. which alſo we the practice of the firſt Antiquity, and its deſuetude complained of by <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> in the end of the fourth Century: and there are few of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the firſt three Centuries, but they mention <hi>Seniores Eccleſiae,</hi> that repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the People in the Government of the Church with the Miniſters.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4ly.</hi> How the Officers of God's Houſe ſhould be qualified, is at length ſet down, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. under the Name of Biſhops (which was the Name of all Church Rulers) and Deacons, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.6.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5ly.</hi> Their work is fully ſet down, both negatively, that they ſhould not be intangled with worldly Affairs, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. where having mentioned Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Miniſters <hi>verſ</hi> 2. he requireth them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3, and 4. as Souldiers to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure hardneſs, and to be abſtracted from worldly Buſineſs, which is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, as much their neceſſity doth permit. Alſo poſitively it is told us in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, that they are directed in this 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.14, 15. and particular Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are given about Preaching, and that in all the parts of it, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2. Cenſures. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4, 5. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.14. Ordination, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6ly.</hi> In all theſe, Miniſters and Elders have no Lordly Authority over the People, but muſt acts as Chriſt's Servants, and theirs, (in order to their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation) 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. yet they have real and proper (though Miniſterial) Authority under Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7ly.</hi> It is not only of Divine Authority natural, that there be a Government in the Church, (Anarchy and Confuſion in any Society being contrary to the Dictates of natural reaſon) but the Lord Jeſus hath poſitively revealed his will in this: He having expreſly committed the Keyes of the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to his Servants, and that for binding and looſing, retaining and remitting of Sins; The Authorotative inflicting of Cenſures, whereby the man is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be free from guilt, and that his Sin is pardoned ſo far as Men can diſcern.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8ly.</hi> What ſhould be the Species of this Government is not left indifferent to Men (whether the Magiſtrat or the Church) to chuſe, but is determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Chriſt, and revealed in the <hi>New Testament;</hi> In that he hath appointed what Officers ſhould be in his Houſe, how they ſhould be Choſen and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180314:3"/>
               <hi>viz,</hi> by Election and Ordination: what ſhould be their Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Work: How they ſhould manage their work, and rule the Church in common: That the Apoſtles committed the Ordination of Miniſters to the <hi>Presbytry,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. and the Cenſures of the Church to a Community, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. And not to one perſon, even in their own time, is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable argument for this; their Example being declarative of the mind of God, where no peculiar reaſon appeareth for their Action.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9ly.</hi> This Government the Lord hath not committed to Magiſtrats, who have no power to Ordain, or Deprive Miniſters, or Elders; nor to Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, or to relax from that Sentence: Nor to Adminiſter, or mannage any part of that Work that is peculiar to the Church, as it is a Religious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; nor to appoint how the Church ſhould be governed: But he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it to the Church Guides, Miniſters and Ruling Elders; for to them are all the Directions about it given in the Word, not to the Magiſtrats; they are to given an account of it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. They did manage it for diverſe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of years, when there was no Magiſtrat that did owne; or countenance Chriſtianity: And there is no hint in Scripture, nor Principle of reaſon that can evince, that this Power ſhould devolve into the hands of the Magiſtrat, when he ſhould become Chriſtian; neither are any Directions given to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrat how he ſhould adminiſter any of the Ordinances of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10ly.</hi> Yet we owne the Civil Magiſtrat as Nurſing Father of the Church and <hi>Cuſtos utriuſque tabulae legis.</hi> Upon which account he is not only to provide <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for the Church, and to procure her Peace and Unity by all good means, (as, repreſſing of Hereſie, Schiſm, and other Diſorders, wherein he is to uſe a judgment of Diſcretion, and not blindly to execute the Sentence of the Church) but alſo may require all the Officers and Members of the Church to do what is their Duty: And that he may (when the Caſe requireth) convocat Synods, and Indict times of Faſting and Thankſgiving: Though for theſe we aſſert and intrinſick Power in the Church, to which that of the Magiſtrat is not privative, but cumulative: For we maintain a twofold Kingdom of Chriſt, one, as God over all men, in which the Magiſtrat is his Vicegerent; another, as Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator over the Church as ſuch, in which he hath Deputed no Magiſtratical, but only Miniſterial Power: We hold alſo, that the Perſons and Actions of Church-men are ſubject to the Civil Magiſtrat, and that they may be puniſh'd when they tranſgreſs the Laws.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11ly.</hi> This Miniſterial governing Power in the Church, the Lord hath not committed to all the Members, nor to all the Males thereof: But hath made a manifeſt diſtinction between Rulers and Ruled, in the Scriptures mentioned already.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12ly.</hi> The Lord hath equally intruſted all his Servants the Miniſters, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the power of diſpenſing the Word, and Sacraments, but alſo with the power of Governing the Church: Which by his appointment, and according
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:180314:4"/>to the practice of the firſt and beſt Ages of the Churches ought to be, and was done in common by Miniſters acting in Parity, and not by a ſingle Prelat ſet over the reſt. This is acknowledge by moſt, and the moſt eminent of our Prelatick Brethren: And muſt be ſo by all of them who do not plead for a Divine Right of <hi>Epiſcopacie.</hi> Beſides that, neither Names, Directions, or Reproofs given to Church-Guides in Scripture, do import any ſuch imparity of Power, nor is there any footſtep of the exerciſe of it in Scripture; to infer this diſpari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Power from that of the Apoſtles, is moſt inconſequential: They being Univerſal, Extraodinary, Unfixed and Temporary Officers; whom the Lord immediatly called, and abrogated their Office with their Death; in that he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther called others to ſucceed in that Power, nor gave any hint that it ſhould be done by the Church. It is as if one ſhould ſay, the Church was once govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Monarchically by a viſible Head (<hi>viz.</hi> while Chriſt was on earth) <hi>ergo,</hi> It ſhould be ſo ſtill: Which no Proteſtant will averr. The Argument in <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> is of the ſame Kidney, they being extraordinary and unfixed Officers, and ſo no precedent for after times. Neither can any Argument be drawn from the Angels of the Churches, words not being often uſed properly in that myſtical Book; and we know that <hi>Thologia Symbolica non eſt Argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tativa.</hi> Beſides that the Angel of <hi>Thyatira</hi> was certainly a Community, being ſpoken to in the Plural Number, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.24. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13 There being no diſparity of power amongſt Miniſters, by Chriſt's grant of power to them: No man can make this Diſparity by ſetting One over the Reſt: Neither can they devolve their power on One of themſelves. For Chriſt hath given no ſuch warrant to Men to diſpoſe of His Ordinance as they ſee fit. And power being delegated to them by him, they cannot ſo commit it to another to exerciſe it for them, as to deprive themſelves of it. Alſo, it being not a <hi>Licenſe</hi> only; but a <hi>Trust,</hi> of which they muſt give an account, they muſt perform the work by themſelves, as they will be anſwerable. But we muſt contract, not being now diſputing, but aſſerting what we ſhall be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to defend as occaſion ſhall be offered.</p>
            <p n="14">14 We aſſert Presbyterial Government to be ſo of Divine Right as We can make no compoſition with men about it, though none ſhall be more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending to them that are otherwiſe minded in what is conſiſtant with Truth and neceſſary Duty than we. Yet it is not alike ſo in all the parts of it. For ſome parts of it are of Chriſt's inſtitution; as the officers of the Church, the Laws, and Cenſures of it. And others of the Dictats of natural Reaſon, (which is alſo a Beam of Divine Light) as that there be a Government and meeting for managing of it, that one preſide in them, that leſſer and greater parts of the Church had their meetings, as Congregational, Claſſical, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial, and National Aſſemblies, for Government; that there be a ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination and appeals amongſt theſe. To require poſitive aſſertions of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, warranting every one of theſe, (though there want not Scripture ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples and other hints to countenance ſeverals of them) is as unreaſonable as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180314:4"/>if we ſhould be called to bring a Text to prove, that we ſhould come in to the publick aſſemblies cloathed and not naked: In an uſual and not in an antiquat Garb.</p>
            <p n="15">15 Whether the Moderator, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of ruling Church meetings ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue for one or more Diets, or for how long a time, is not determined by any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Chriſt, nor by any general dictate of natural Light: Yet we judge a conſtant Moderator, highly inconvenient, and by all means to be ſhunned: For if he be impoſed on the meeting, it is an encroachment on their intrinſick power of governing themſelves in ſuch things as are peculiar to them. And though choſen by themſelves, fatal; and conſtant examples together with the inclinations of men to uſurpation, do ſhew it to have ſo violent tendency to Lordly Prelacy, as rarely doeth it fail of the bad effects, nor can be expected not to Iſſue in it.</p>
            <p>We maintain that no Church Judicature ought to cognoſce of Affairs of State, nor of Mens civil Rights, or Intereſts, except their advice ſhould be ſought by the Magiſtrat concerning Sin or Duty in any ſuch matter: As if the thing be manifeſtly Scandalous, and evidently dangerous to the intereſt of Religion, and the Souls of Men. Neither do they inflict any puniſhment ſave Spiritual Cenſures. Their work is to enquire into, and declare controverted Truths; to cenſure Scandalous Sinners: to try and ordain Miniſters: to abſolve the penitent by applying the comforts of the Goſpel to them, and ſuch like: Wherefore there is no Ground of Fear that they ſhould Claſh, or Cope with Magiſtrat, unleſs they go beyond their line; in which caſe they fall under the Magiſtrats coercive power.</p>
            <p n="16">16 The way how men come into any office or power in the Church, is by Election of the people, which deſigneth the Perſon (in which Election as in other things they are to be under the Conduct and Regulation of the Church Guides) and ordination, by laying on of the hands of the Presbytery, which is the mean of communicating authority to him: and the former of theſe ought to preceed the latter: For we find no warrand for a <hi>Ministerium Vagum</hi> in the Church, ſeeing even in times of great trouble and Perſecution we read of none ordained by the Apoſtles, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> with the ſuffrages of the People.</p>
            <p n="17">17 Though ſuperintendency, that is a power of inſpection delegated from the Church to one, uſed in caſe of neceſſity when a qualified Miniſter could hardly be had in a Province: he might for a time be appointed to overſee them who could do little more than read the word publickly, that is no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for bringing qualified Miniſters under that ſubjection in a conſtituted Church, where there are (through the mercy of God) competent number of Miniſters.</p>
            <p>If our Principles be rightly underſtood, we confidently hope they will ſuggeſt grounds of anſwer for moſt of the objections made againſt us, to the minds of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180314:5"/>the intelligent and unbyaſſed: Yet we ſhall endeavour to afford ſome farther light this way alſo.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is objected (or rather we are reproached with) by ſome, that Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterial Church Government is inconſiſtant with Civil Government. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. A ſimple denial is enough to ſtop the mouth of ſuch bold Aſſerters: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath the World yet ſeen any topick (except Calumnies) whereby this could be pretended to be proved. 2. Experience proveth the contrary, Civil Government is advantageouſly mannaged in ſeveral of the moſt eminent of the reformed Churches, with that diſcipline of Chriſt's Houſe that we plead for. And our own land is a confounding inſtance that might ſtop the mouth of impudence it ſelf, wherein Presbytery commenced with the Reformation from Pupery, and continued with much Peace, till ambitious Men, by labouring to unſettle it, did diſturb, and at laſt overturn the State. 3. We have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhewed how we give to <hi>Caeſar</hi> that which is <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and to God that which is Gods; neither can our Adverſarie make any Power appear to be due to the Magiſtrat, but what we allow Him: Indeed <hi>Eraſtians</hi> do require for the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrat ſome Power that the Presbyterians cannot approve of: But this is not peculiar to us, but common to all that aſſert a Government in the Church di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from that of the State. Which is the principle of <hi>Papiſts, Prelatiſts,</hi> (that are only ſuch) and <hi>Independents,</hi> as well as it is ours. 4. Our obedience to Magiſtrats in all their Lawful commands, and our peaceful ſufferings of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt violence are notour to all that can behold us with an unprejudiced Eye. And if inſtances can be given to the contrary, the diſloyalty of ſome is not to be imputed to all; (for what party of men hath not afforded ſuch inſtances) and where the peace was broken by Men of our way (which were but a few) it was the fruit of ſuch inſupportable Severities and Hardſhips, as even they could not have born, who blame others for that practiſe: As late Inſtances do make manifeſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is next objected that Presbytery and Monarchy are inconſiſtant, <hi>No Biſhop, no King;</hi> at leaſt it is not ſo adapted to Monarchy as Prelacy is; and the Government of the Church ſhould be ſo moulded as it may beſt ſute that of the State. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The falſhood of the Aſſertion and Maxim, is evident from what hath been ſaid: Presbytery and Monarchy have well conſiſted in our own Land, and in <hi>France:</hi> 2 None maintain more loyal Principles towards Kings than Presbyterians do, who think themſelves oblidged to fear God and Honour the King, and were alwayes ready to obey him in the Lord. 'Tis true they cannot give him Unlimited Obedience: But this is not as they are Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, but as they are men of Conſcience, and will obey God rather than Man, which I hope the Objecters will not ſay is peculiar to Presbyterians; If they do, and plead for the publick Conſcience (as ſome of them have done) to the laying aſide the uſe of particular Conſciences in the actions that are moral, which is to introduce practical Atheiſm) They do not hurt our
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180314:5"/>cauſe, but their own. 3. Our practice hath alſo been Loyal in abhorring the Murder of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, and in contributing the moſt effectual en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to reſtore His Son: And in owning and ſubmitting to a King of a contrary Religion, ſo long as our Religion and Liberties were in any tolerable ſafety, or the Laws that were the meaſure of our obedience were any way re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded; and what was then done, was not by us alone. 4. It is boldly alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged but not proved, that the Church Government ſhould be fram'd according to that of the State; for that may be various, but this is one: And was ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the old Teſtament, though the Civil Government varied.</p>
            <p n="3">3 'Tis ſaid that Presbyterians encroach on the Authority of the Magiſtrat, by medling with ſtate Affairs. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1 Our Principle in this is already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared. And whatever inſtances of former times, this allegation may ſeem to be built on, had their riſe from Stateſmen taking the advice of Church-men in their Aſſemblies, who ſometimes gave advice contrary to the inclination of the leading Men of the State: And if their Zeal for a good Intereſt led them at any time to preſs their advice with Reaſons and Threatnings from the Word of God; And if ſome exceſs did happen this way, the blame lay on them who gave the firſt riſe to it. Beſides this when the actings of Rulers have a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and direct tendency to lead People into ſinful Courſes, (ſuch as impoſing of unlawful Oaths, and engaging People in a falſe Religion) who could be ſilent without unfaithfulneſs to God, and cruelty both to the Souls of Rulers and People? Another anſwer may be, by retorting this Argument on the prelatick Clergy; Do not Biſhops ſit in the Councils, and interpoſe directly and formally in affairs of State, which Presbyterians never pretended to.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The rigidity of Presbyterians is objected. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1 Can any man have the brow to compare the rigidity of Presbyterians, with that of either <hi>Bapiſts</hi> or <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latists,</hi> either in bearing with no diſſent from their way, even in the leaſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and which themſelves count indifferent, or in the Bloody and cruel way of Perſecuting ſuch as diſſent; by Maſſacres, Inquiſitions, horrid Tortures, Impriſonment, Fining, and ſtrange Severities: Is there any thing that can be alledg'd againſt <hi>Presbyterians</hi> that can be once compared with the Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that many in the weſt of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and elſewhere, have lately Endured? Yea <hi>Independents</hi> cannot compare with the Moderation of <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> For they (moſt of them) will not communicat with any but of their own way; And ſo with none but thoſe of their own Congregation, which is far from Our way. As for <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Quakers,</hi> They owne none for Members of the Church but Men of their own Stamp: So that it may be on good ground ſaid, That <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are the moſt Moderate of any Party that pretend to Religion. 2. That which Men call Rigidity in <hi>Presbyterians</hi> is moſtly againſt Mens Immoralities, that are unqueſtionably ſuch: If other Men be Gentle to theſe, it may recommend them to wicked Mens good liking, but will not render them acceptable to God: This ſtrictneſs of diſciplin againſt ſcandalous Sins, is injoined in Scripture, and we go not beyond the bounds there ſet; we rebuke
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:180314:6"/>ſuch before all, we do not puniſh them in their Bodies or Purſes; and our ſtrictneſs falleth very far ſhort of that of the primitive times; as every one who hath read any thing of the Hiſtory of the ancient Church knoweth, both their <hi>Catechumeni</hi> were detained from Church priviledges; and their <hi>Penitents</hi> put to long and hard <hi>Pennance,</hi> at another rate then any thing that we do. 3. Wherein lyeth the Rigidity of Our diſcipline? Do not our Miniſters deal with them who fall into ſcandalous ſins, with all Meekneſs and Tenderneſs, admoniſhing them, laying before them the Evil and Danger of their way, the neceſſity of Repentance, the hope of Mercy through Chriſt that there is to the penitent. It is our way, even where the Sinner is moſt obſtinate and rejecteth all advice, to wait for many weeks, before we proceed to Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, that, that dreadful Sentence, if poſſible, may be prevented. We give publick Admonition three ſeveral Lords dayes, and ſometimes oftener: We pour out Prayers to God, not only in ſecret, but with the Congregation as long; that the Sinner may be turned from his evil way; And after all this we uſe to wait Patiently for the Mans Repentance: If he appear Penitent, the Sentence doth not paſs againſt him; and after Sentence is paſt upon the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Sinner, if afterward he ſhew any ſigns of Repentance, how readily is he received into the Church again, and we chearfully confirm our love to him. And where Church Cenſures are uſed, it is not for Worldly matters (not paying Church dues, as is the practice of ſome others) not for ſmall offences, but for Groſs and ſcandalous Sins. 4. For their ſeveritie toward ſuch as differ from them in Principles, they think it their Duty not to bear them that are Evil, and to try them that ſay they are <hi>Apoſtles, and are not;</hi> They have a zeal againſt Errour, Diſorders and Uſurpations in the Church, and cannot underſtand how they who do not owne <hi>Presbyterial</hi> Government, ſhould be the mannagers of it: Yet can uſe that Moderation (and reſolve to do ſo when op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity ſhall be put in their hand) as not to deny Church Communion to any ſober and Religious Perſon, though of a contrary ſentiment to them, in theſe inferior of Truth.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5ly.</hi> Another Objection, is from the Indiſcretion of the preſent Miniſters of this way: Their want of that Learning, Prudence, and other good parts that may fit them to manage ſo great a Truſt, as is the Government of the Church. <hi>Anſw.</hi> We know theſe are the diminutive thoughts that our adverſaries have of us: And we have not ſuch high thoughts of our ſelves, as to magnifie our ſelves: We have cauſe to be humbled, (as we hope we are, in ſome meaſure) for our imperfections, both in Gifts, and Grace: Yet we may, and muſt (being thus put to it) ſay, that there want not men amongſt us, who fall not ſhort in Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Qualifications, of them who have lately had the Rule of the Church; and for the generality of us, it is the Opinion of the World, and of unbyaſſed men (yea, even of ſome, that are not of our way) that theſe of the other party have no cauſe in their Glorying over us in this. 2. Church Government doth not require any great degree of politick Accompliſhment: A plain Man
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180314:6"/>who underſtandeth the Laws of Chriſt, and the Scripture Directions concerning Cenſures, is fitter to Govern the Church, than a great Statesman is. 3. Any Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion that of late years hath appeared in our Conduct, may and ſhould be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to our want of Liberty to govern the Church: Every one (among Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and People) did what was right in his own Eyes, and we do not deny, but there are ſome Indiſcreet perſons among us, as there are in all parties: And even wiſe Men in our Circumſtances, could not ſhun ſome acts that might ſeem In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet, either to Adverſaries, or to leſs conſidering Perſons.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6ly.</hi> The Diviſions of <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are objected. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Where are theſe not to be found; neither Biſhop nor Pope have been able to keep them out of the Church, or from among their own Party. 2. Our Diviſions we do not deny, or approve, we are men of like Paſſions with others; we labour to ſhun Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions as much as is poſſible, and through Grace have come to more Unity than they who reproach us with our Diviſions. 3. The Diviſions that were among us, as we deny not that our Miſtakes and Corruptions had a hand in them, ſo we know that enemies were active to promote and heighten them: which though it excuſe not us <hi>a toto,</hi> yet it doth <hi>a tanto,</hi> and put our enemies in <hi>mala fide</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach us with them. 4. The Unity that the Prelatick party made in the Church, was like that of a conquering Tyrant, who beholdeth all that oppoſe him, ſlain before him; there was peace to the King and <hi>Haman,</hi> when there was none to the people of God; the Unity of ſome, is a combination in error, and the reſult of a Conqueſt over mens Conſciences, that now dare not mutter againſt the Luſts of their Impoſing Task maſters: we think contending about Truth, more deſirable than ſuch peace: It is known that our Church enjoyed ſuch Unity for many years after the Reformation, as was Celebrated by Churches abroad, as is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident from the Preface to <hi>Corpus Confeſſionum,</hi> till ambitious men began to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble her with their Innovations, and Uſurpations, and ſo were the cauſe of Diviſion.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Many object, that if <hi>Presbyterians</hi> get Power, they will force all to make publick Repentance who have owned <hi>Biſhops,</hi> taken the <hi>Test,</hi> or other <hi>Oaths</hi> that they diſlike. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Our Principle is, that publick Scandals ought to be publickly rebuked; yet there are Caſes in which the ſtrictneſs of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline in this matter, may and muſt be relaxed: I ſhall name two. 1. When the matter of Offence is controverted, and the ſinful practice is from the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>information of the Conſcience: where the matter is not of the higheſt moment, and the perſon appeareth Conſcientiouſly to follow his Light, Church Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline may then be forborn. 2. When the fault is univerſal, either the whole, or the greater part, or a great part of the Church is guilty: The rigour of Cenſure (that otherwiſe might be due) is to be abated, even the Primitive Church, though very ſevere in Diſcipline, uſed a great <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in this Caſe: When many, or moſt had fallen in Perſecution, though the Crime was of the higheſt nature, even denying the Faith. A general Humiliation of the whole Church may be in ſtead of particular application of Cenſures; I hope there is no cauſe of fear from Men of ſuch moderate Principles. If in this, or any thing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180314:7"/>elſe, we have been chargeable with Exceſs, (as who can clear himſelf of all blame) I hope our riper Thoughts Studies, and Sufferings, (by the Bleſſing of God on them) hath taught us, and will engage us to let our Moderation be known to all men; conſidering that the Lord is at hand: And though we have been ſeverly Beaten by our Fellow Servants; yet we will ſtand in awe, and be lothe that the Lord, when he cometh, ſhould find us ſo doing to them.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8ly.</hi> Some Object, That in this way, Miniſters many Domineer over Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, even the greateſt Men, at their pleaſure. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Beſide that they muſt walk by the Rule ſet down in the Word; and if they exceed that bounds, they may be curbed by Superior Judicatories: Or if their Inſolence amount to the diſturbing of the Peace, the Magiſtrat may reſtrain them: we ſay, beſide this, the Miniſters do nothing alone, but with the peoples Repreſentatives, the Elders, who may be of the Nobles, or any other Rank, as they are qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified for that work, and choſen to it by the Church.</p>
            <p>Some other Objections are toſſed among Men that talk of theſe things, which do not ſo much concern <hi>Presbyterial Government</hi> in general, as ſome parts of it, or things about it, that are now in agitation. The 9th. Objection then, may be fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med againſt the taking away the Election of Miniſters by Patrons, <hi>viz.</hi> That if that be done, men of Note, and Intereſt in Pariſhes may be over-ruled by the multitude (which often is ignorant and heady) and have Miniſters impoſed on them. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1 That Patronages are an intollerable Grievance, and yoke of Bondage on the Church, and have always been the cauſe of peſtering the Church with a bad Miniſtry: and a temptation to Intrants to pleaſe the Patron (farther than to his Edification) rather than to pleaſe God: Beſide the Simoniacal buying &amp; felling of Goſpel Ordinances, that frequently, &amp; in all times have attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Device of Men: But (which is worſt of all) that it is a direct croſſing Chriſt's Inſtitution, and a robbing his people of the priviledge he hath bequea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed to them: Theſe things, I ſay, are full proved elſewhere. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if it be ſuppoſed that the Inconvenience mentioned ſhould follow from taking away of patronages, yet it will not (I hope) move them who regard Chriſt's Inſtitutions; or the good of his Church, the Salvation, and Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Souls, to be for their continuance. 2 The ſame inconvenience was apt to follow on popular Election in other Ages of the Church; and yet in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles times, and in the firſt and beſt Ages, till the ſeventh or eight Century, or latter, patronages were not ſettled in the Church; they came in among the lateſt Antichriſtian Corruptions and Uſurpations; The primitive Chriſtians were not ſo tender of their Grandeur, and ſuch priviledges as their rank in the World gave them, nor ſo little tender of the Liberties of the Church, and the Intereſt of Chriſtians, as ſuch. And if any ſuch pretenſions appeared to be owned by the Grandees of theſe times, they met with a ſevere Check, and that in leſſer matters than acclaiming a Power of chooſing Miniſters for the whole Church: as appeareth by the <hi>Apostles</hi> reproving the Diſtinction even in the Seats in their Aſſemblies, that was made between the Man with the <hi>Gold
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180314:7"/>Ring</hi> and gay Cloathing, and the Man in Vile Raiment: We are content to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low great Men all due Reſpect, but not to complement them with what is Chriſt's Legacy to his People. And therefore we hope That they who are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſubject themſelves to the Laws of Chriſt, will be content to ſtand on equal Ground (tho we be far from aiming at the Levelling principle in other things) with their poor Brethren in the Church, with reſpect to Church pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, which belong not to Men as Poor or Rich, as Great or Small; but as they are Chriſt's Diſciples. 3. It is carefully to be Obſerved that the Election of a Miniſter is not to be left to the Management of the confuſed Rabble, (tho' the meaneſt adult male Member of the Church hath a Right to aſſent or diſſent) but it is to be ordered by the Elderſhip, and that under the inſpection of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery (and by the Presbytery where no congregational Elderſhip is) in the Number of which Elders it is to be ſuppoſed, that Heretors and Men of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in the Paroch will be, if they be tolerably qualified for, and will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, ſuch an Office, and then they have a ſpecial hand in the Election, and cannot complain of being impoſed upon: And the Elderſhip is to exclude from having an hand in the Election, them that are ſcandalous, groſly ignorant, Heady and Schiſmatick, or any way diſorderly. And if Diviſions fall in, the Elders are Judges of the difference between the two Parties; and are to conſider the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons on both Hands; and to ponder and weigh, as well as to Number the Votes. They ought alſo to exclude from voting in ſuch Elections all ſuch as are not fixed Members of the congregation. And to lay more weight on the ſuffrages of them that are more fixed, and leſs on them that are otherwiſe, <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris paribus.</hi> For though Chriſtianity maketh one a Member of the Church Catholick, yet a fixed abode is needfull to make one a Member of, and to give a ſhare in the priviledges of that particular Flock. But how to limit this fixation is not eaſie: For though ſome be manifeſtly unfixed as ſervants; and others are manifeſtly fixed, as ancient inhabitants who are like to continue long in that place; yet there may be a middle ſort who cannot be determined by General Rules, but it muſt be left to the prudence of the Church to judge in this. If theſe things be duely conſidered, Great Men need not fear having a Miniſter obtruded on them; eſpecially if we add, that Men of intereſt uſually are able to influence thoſe that live under them, or that do depend upon them. 4. In the times wherein Patronages were taken away by Law, Men of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and reſpect found no cauſe to complain of being impoſed upon, but the Church laid down ſuch directions (as may be ſeen in the Acts of the General Aſſembly <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 4. 1649. <hi>Seſs.</hi> 40. And the conſtant practice of the Church was to give ſuch deference to them, as they were Generally ſatisfied with the Elections: And they may ſtill be perſwaded, that it will be the care of <hi>Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips</hi> and <hi>Presbytries</hi> to do nothing that they can Juſtly complain of. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that it may be preſumed that no Miniſter, who regardeth his being uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, or his own Peace and Comfort, will enter into a place with the diſlike <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any conſiderable part of the People, either for Number or Quality. If it
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:180314:8"/>be objected that there were great Diviſions and Tumults about Elections, in and about the Year. 1650. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 1. So there were in the primitive Church, which the <hi>Advocats</hi> for Patronages uſe as an Argument againſt our Opinion, and yet that Church did not think of ſuch a Remedy, as putting the Election in the hand of one ſingle Perſon, nor of taking it from the People. 2. At the time mentioned there was a lamentable Schiſm in the Church about other Matters; and therefore it was no wonder it appeared in this Matter alſo, People were for chooſing Miniſters that were of the ſame Sentiment with them, about the things then in Controverſie, and this Schiſm was Induſtriouſly kept up and promoted by the Rulers, that then had enſlaved this Nation by force of Arms, and made uſe of Our Factions to wreath their Yoke on our Necks. It is a wide conſequence to inferr from this, that the priviledge of chooſing their own Paſtors ſhould alwiſe be taken from the People of God. 3. When di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions appear in this matter, the controverſie is to be decided by the Seſſion, or Presbytery, Synod, or General Aſſemblie; And if it Amount to the breach of the Peace, the Magiſtrat is to interpoſe his Authority: Theſe are the proper remedies of ſuch diviſions, and not to deprive both parties of that which is their Right and Chriſts grant to them, becauſe they cannot agree about it: It were a ſtrange way of compoſing Civil contending about <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> if that which they contend about ſhould be taken from both, and given to a third Perſon; the better way is, the Judge competent is to decide in favour of him who is found to have the beſt Right (if Arbitrators cannot compromiſe the matter) So it is here.</p>
            <p>Another Objection (the 10) Is concerning a queſtion that ariſeth from the preſent circumſtances of this Church, under which it is judged neceſſary, that the Government of the Church ſhould be in its firſt ſettlement in the hands on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of them who are known to be truly Presbyterian. Before we conſider what is objected againſt this, It may be needful to lay down the caſe, and the grounds of the neceſſity of what we deſire, reſulting from it. It is then to be conſidered, That the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> hath almoſt ever been Presbyterian: It received that Government with Chriſtianity, and retained it while the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Doctrine and Government prevailed in other parts; as hath been of late made appear. And after it had been overrun by Popery, it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by Presbyters; and that Government as it is founded on Scripture, ſo it hath continued in this Church ever ſince the Reformation, ſave that it had ſome ſhort interruption, which did always breed diſqueit in the minds of People, and troubles in the Nation, and ſufferings to ſome of the moſt ſober and beſt of the Miniſters and People: And when in the Year 1662. That Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment was ſuppreſſed, and Prelacy ſet up by an Act of Parliament; the deed was never conſented to by the National Church, but Presbytery, as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> been ſettled by the Authority of the Church and State, ſo continued, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> continue ſettled by the Authority of the Church: Whence it may ration<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> be Deduced, that the Miniſters that entred by and under Prelacy, neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:180314:8"/>nor have any Right to be Rulers in the Preſbyterian Church; they having had no Call nor Authority given them from her (whatever they might have in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Church that the State ſet up in the Nation, beſide the Church that then was in beeing, from which a great Body of Miniſters and People did diſſent, which Authority they were never ſuffered to exerciſe even in their own Church.) It is alſo to be conſidered, that on this happy Revolution the King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament have been pleaſed to aboliſh Prelacy, and have declared their Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution by their Authority to ſettle Presbyterian Government. From this it followeth, that the Prelatick Clergy ſhould not be admitted to a ſhare in this Government: Except ſuch of them as ſhall by the Presbyterian Church be found qualified for the Miniſtry, and ſuch from whom there is no hazard of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturning that Government that now is intended to be eſtabliſhed: For they being more in number than the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> is it to be imagined that <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian</hi> Government can be ſafe in their Hands, or that they will not erect a prelacy in the Church, or ſomething in ſtead of it, or ſome way that is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant with Presbytery in its purity? And there being many among them known to be Inſufficient, Scandalous, or erroneous, it is not poſſible that the Church can be purged of ſuch, if they have the Government, but rather there is an hazard that the beſt Men ſhould be caſt out, and that by Church Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, leaſt they ſhould ſtand in the way of their Deſigns. Wherefore as they have no juſt Right to ſuch power, ſo Neceſſity (which <hi>quicquid coegit, defendit</hi>) doth barr their Exerciſe of ſuch power in the preſent juncture. Mean while Presbyterians do declare, that they do not deſire that all theſe Men ſhould be reſtrained from the parochial exerciſe of their Miniſtry. And that who ever among them (as ſoon as the Church can be in caſe to purge her ſelf) is not proved to be Inſufficient, Scandalous, Erroneous, or extremly negligent, ſhall be cordially received into Her Society, and have the full Exerciſe of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry; and that where uncontroverted Scandals cannot be charged on them, none ſhall be dealt with as Scandalous, becauſe of their having had a Hand in this late publick Defection.</p>
            <p>Theſe things thus laid down, let us hear what is objected againſt this courſe. 1ſt. This is to ſet up Prelacy among Miniſters, even while it is ſo much decry'd, that a few ſhould have Rule of the Churches, and the reſt excluded. <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is no Prelacy, but a making diſtinction between Miniſters of one Society, and theſe of another: Though they be Miniſters, they are not Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Presbyterian Church, they have deported from it; we have conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in the good old way that they and we profeſſed: It is not then unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, that if they will return to that Society, they ſhould be admitted by it, and not be Impoſed on it, to overturn it. At the Reformation from <hi>Popery,</hi> was it a <hi>Prelacy</hi> in the few <hi>Proteſtant Miniſters,</hi> that they were not willing to let the <hi>Popiſh Prieſts</hi> govern the Church? Or did <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> pretend to any power over <hi>Tobiah, Sanballat,</hi> and their party, that they would not ſuffer them to build with them? Pardon theſe Compariſons, they are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:180314:9"/>to parallel our Burthen with either of theſe ſorts of Men, except in this, that they are not of the <hi>Presbyterian Church,</hi> more than thoſe others were of the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> or <hi>Jewiſh Church;</hi> and that there is hazard from them to our way, as well as there was from the other to their wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. By this means the leſſer party in the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhall exclude the greater from the Government. <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is not abſurd, where the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er party have left the Church they were of; and the leſſer had abode in it, or rather are left as the conſtituent Members of it: And when the greater party hath ſet up another frame of a Church, which they are now forced to part with, when they would return to the former way, they cannot Incorporate again with them who abode in it, without their Conſent; eſpecially where this conſent is ready to be given on any tollerable Security for the way that the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer party doth owne, and the other departed from.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. What warrant is there for leaving to theſe men the Parochial exerci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of their Miniſtry, and to deprive them of the other part of it, ſeeing the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the Miniſtry in Teaching and Ruling is <hi>Quid Indiviſum. Anſ.</hi> There are two Reaſons for this; one is the neceſſity of the Church, which for ſuch a critical <hi>interim</hi> as our lot is fallen into, may warrant that, which out of ſuch an exigence, and for a conſtant continuance in the Church were unwarrantable. It is neceſſary on the one hand, that the Pariſhes be not deprived of their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, leaſt a great part of the Countrey ſhould be deſtitute of all Goſpel Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances: It is as neceſſary on the other hand, that they have not Ruling Power in the Church with the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> leſt that Government which Chriſt hath inſtituted, and which is now deſigned to be Settled, be over-turned. And we know, that many things may be done in <hi>turbato Statu Eccleſiae,</hi> (ſuch as we now are in) which ought not to be allowed in <hi>paccato Eccleſiae Statu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Another reaſon is, we do neither deny their Teaching, nor their Ruling Power: Yet Teaching being common to the one Church way with the other we may well allow to them the exerciſe of that among us, while Ruling being different in their way and ours, and the Principle that they hold in it being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſive of our way, it is rational to deny them a ſhare among us. Not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt on further Objections, whatever inconveniences may ſeem to follow on this conduct, may be anſwered by the force of Neceſſity already held forth, and obviated by the ſpeedy ſettling the Church upon its right Baſis.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
